Guide to the Donald Sutherland MacIvor Papers 1893-1972
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Donald Sutherland MacIvor Papers
1893-1972
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula 406-243-2053 Missoula, MT 59812 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 103
MacIvor, Donald Sutherland
0.5 linear feet
Donald S. MacIvor was a Northern Pacific Railroad employee. This collection contains general correspondence, financial records, legal documents, clippings, photographs and miscellany.
Biographical Note
Donald Sutherland MacIvor was born in the late nineteenth century, probably in Nova Scotia. In 1903 or 1904 he began work for the Northern Pacific Railroad as an agent and telegraph operator. He worked for the railroad in Drummond, Bearmouth, Arlee, Ronan, and Ravalli before locating to Missoula, Montana, in 1945 or 1946. He married Nellie (Helen) Crockett of Hopewell, Nova Scotia in the early 1900s. The MacIvors retired in Missoula. Nellie died in 1972 and Donald in the mid 1970s.
This collection contains general correspondence, financial records, legal documents, clippings, and miscellany. Included are personal letters, 1893-1972; records of household finances, 1946-1957; income tax forms, 1936-1972; certificates, 1887-1935; memorial records, 1966-1972; and newspaper clippings. Two letters to the MacIvors dated Jan. 21, 1922 and February 8, 1922, give details of an automobile trip from Butte, Montana to Portland, Oregon. Two folders of previously unincorporated photographs were added into the collection in 2006.
This collection is divided into six series:
Series I: General Correspondence, 1893-1972 and undated, 4 folders
Series II: Financial Records, 1936-1972, 2 folders
Series III: Legal Documents, 1887-1935 and undated, 1 folder
Series IV: Clippings, 1969 and undated, 1 folder
Series V: Memorials, c. 1907-1972, 1 folder
Series VI: Photographs, c. 1900s-1950s, 2 folders
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
Gift of Kenneth Daniels, 1981.
Songs of the 85th Overseas Battalion, Canadian Expedition Force, are located in the Special Collections.
The Historical Museum at Fort Missoula holds a collection of bibles and high school drawings from 1894 that were once part of this collection.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Family papers--Montana--Missoula
Automobile travel--Northwest, Pacific; Canadian Americans--Montana--Missoula
MacIvor family; McIvor family
Montana; City and Town Life
- General Correspondence, 1893-1972 and undated; Series I; 4 folders
  This series includes early personal correspondence to Nell and her sister, Eliza, from both their brother, Asa Crockett, and father, Daniel W. Crockett. There is later personal correspondence between Nell and Donald MacIvor. A few letters concern Mr. MacIvor's attempt to get a temporary release from the railroad in 1918 in order to gain an officer's commission in the army. Instead of gaining an officer's commission, Mr. MacIvor became chairman of the United War Campaign which raised funds for the war effort. Folder 2 contains a practice exam given to immigrants who desired United States citizenship. This folder also includes two letters describing an automobile trip from Butte, Montana to Portland, Oregon in 1921. Folder 3 contains a description of a trip to Jerusalem from Beirut in 1951 and other correspondence to the MacIvors describing life in the Middle East in the 1950s.
  - 1893-1900 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - 1906-1938 and undated (Box-folder 1/2)
  - 1941-1966 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - 1967-1972 and undated (Box-folder 1/4)
- Financial Records, 1936-1972; Series II; 2 folders
  This series contains records of the MacIvor's household finances while living in Missoula from 1944-1957. Examples of expenses included furnace oil, electric lights, and rent. A primary source of income was Mr. MacIvor's railroad pension. The second folder contains the MacIvor's state and federal income tax forms from 1936-1972.
  - Household Finances, 1944-1957 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Income Tax Returns, 1936-1972 (Box-folder 1/6)
- Legal Documents, 1887-1935 and undated; Series III; 1 folder
  This series contains Nell's birth certificate, high school diploma, and a Diploma of Progress from the Methodist Episcopal Church. It also includes Donald's Military Registration Certificate, Notice of Military Classification, and membership cards for the Liberty Loan Committee.
  - Certificates, 1887-1935 and undated (Box-folder 1/7)
- Clippings, 1969 and undated; Series IV; 1 folder
  This series primarily includes newspaper clippings about Judge Asa James Crockett, who was related to Nell.
  - Judge Asa James Crockett, 1969 and undated (Box-folder 1/8)
- Memorials, Series V
  This series contains a memorial book for Judge Asa James Crockett who died in 1966. This book includes a brief family history. There is also a memorial for Nell MacIvor, who died in 1972. There is an address book and two valentines. The valentines were sent to Nell from Donald dated circa 1907.
  - Memorial Records, Address Book, and Valentines, 1907-1972 and undated (Box-folder 1/9)
- Photographs, Series VI
  Photographs include formal portraits and snapshots of people and scenes, including images from the Bearmouth, Montana, and Hopewell, Nova Scotia.
  - Photographs (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Photographs (Box-folder 1/11)